<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Berlin Milan Moving Job on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/berlin-milan-moving-job/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Berlin Milan Moving Job on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/berlin-milan-moving-job/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to Germany!</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/moving-to-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/moving-to-germany/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And so here we are. After less than a year of marriage, my wife and I are relocating to a new Country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been living in Milan, Italy since we got married, and, I will admit, we have loved the city. Milan is, as I often say, the Italian idea of what a metropolis would be. While it has all the characteristics of a modern European city, it is also very, very Italian. It is a city definitely worth visiting and a lovely place to work and live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from September the 1st I am going to be working in Berlin, Germany for a very big international IT company that has its headquarters in the German capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are absolutely thrilled by this new opportunity and we had actually been looking at going to live in a bigger European city for a while, so this job opportunity does indeed come as a sort of &amp;#8216;answer&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working with lots of extremely skilled professionals, which makes the whole thing very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Berlin does look like an impressively dynamic city, with many creative people and a start up culture that is probably second to none in Europe. And somehow I find the German culture quite fascinating, so I am happy that I&amp;#8217;ll be able to learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Germany, here we come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: if you happen to come to Berlin in the next months and you have anything interesting to share, feel free to drop me a line and I will be happy to have a coffee with you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>