<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tutorials on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/tutorials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tutorials on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/tutorials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to use Fat Free framework from the command line</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-use-fat-free-framework-from-the-command-line/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-use-fat-free-framework-from-the-command-line/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every good framework should allow you to easily create/execute commands from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Command-line_interface&#34; title=&#34;command line&#34;&gt;command line&lt;/a&gt; (also called &lt;em&gt;shell&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;terminal&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command line is incredibly helpful and in some cases (e.g. when executing &lt;em&gt;cron jobs&lt;/em&gt; or particularly big scripts that make extensive use of your server&amp;#8217;s resources) simply unavoidable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will show you how to execute your scripts using the command line and work with a standard Fat Free application to illustrate them. It assumes then that you already have Fat Free framework installed and working on your server. If you don&amp;#8217;t know how to do this, please refer to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/articles/how-to-use-the-fat-free-php-framework&#34;&gt;earlier tutorial&lt;/a&gt; that I have written for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.digitalocean.com&#34;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, while executing commands from the command line with Fat Free framework is fairly easy, it is not very well documented and you might find yourself in trouble if you need to use that functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-your-commands:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Set up your commands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To set up your command, create a new route in your application&amp;#8217;s bootstrap page (if you have followed the &amp;#8220;set up&amp;#8221; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/articles/how-to-use-the-fat-free-php-framework&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;, then it should be &lt;code&gt;index.php&lt;/code&gt;). To do that, just add a new routing directive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$f3-&amp;gt;route(&#39;GET /command&#39;, function($f3) {
    echo &amp;quot;Here our command starts&amp;quot;.PHP_EOL;
    // lots of operations here
    echo &amp;quot;Done! Be proud!&amp;quot;;
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be sure that your command will only be executed through the command line, then the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.php.net/manual/en/reserved.constants.php&#34;&gt;PHP_SAPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function will be a life-saver for you (this is function that returns the type of interface in use between PHP and the web server). For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$f3-&amp;gt;route(&#39;GET /command&#39;, function($f3) {
    if(php_sapi_name() == &amp;quot;cli&amp;quot;) {
        //In cli-mode = the interface in use is the command line (cli)
        echo &amp;quot;Here our command starts&amp;quot;.PHP_EOL;
        // lots of operations here
        echo &amp;quot;Done! Be proud!&amp;quot;;
    } else {
        //Not in cli-mode
        echo &amp;quot;You&#39;re not allowed to execute this operation&amp;quot;;
    }
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;execute-your-command:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Execute your command&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now comes the fun part. In order to execute the command that you have just set up, open a terminal application and write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd /your/application/path // go to the directory where Fat Free is installed
php index.php &amp;quot;/command&amp;quot; // execute your command
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, if there are no errors in your code, you should see the output of your command on screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might of course sometimes need to save the output somewhere, so that you may check it at any time, especially if you execute your command as a cron job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that is the case, then write this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;php index.php &amp;quot;/command&amp;quot; &amp;gt; /path/to/file.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;troubleshooting:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;server-variables:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Server variables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might encounter issues with Web server-related functions and variables in your code (e.g. &lt;code&gt;$_SERVER[&#39;HTTP_HOST&#39;]&lt;/code&gt;), which will inevitably return an error, since the command line won&amp;#8217;t recognize them. Here is where the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.php.net/manual/en/reserved.constants.php&#34;&gt;PHP_SAPI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; function could turn out to be extremely valuable, as it will allow you to detect whether your code is being executed by a web server or through the command line. This is what you might want to write to avoid this type of error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$http_host = (php_sapi_name() == &amp;quot;cli&amp;quot;) ? &amp;quot;cli&amp;quot; : $_SERVER[&#39;HTTP_HOST&#39;];
echo $http_host;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of just:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo $_SERVER[&#39;HTTP_HOST&#39;]; // this will not work on the command line
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;paths:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Paths&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the command line will not recognize relative paths within your PHP code. So, be sure to always use the absolute path when you, for instance, handle a file. A path that looks like &lt;code&gt;/files/log/log.txt&lt;/code&gt; will then have to become something like &lt;code&gt;/var/www/html/thisismyapp.ie/files/log/log.txt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:23e234fcc1d49b9af94cfc871f2e6b19&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have seen, using the command line with a framework like Fat Free is easy and does not imply changing a lot of things in your code. That means that you can easily call the same functions from both browser and command line, which makes your life easier (whereas with some other frameworks you have to put your commands in a different place, which means additional work).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make your website available offline with HTML5</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/make-your-website-available-offline-with-html5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/make-your-website-available-offline-with-html5/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One of the really cool things &lt;strong&gt;HTML5&lt;/strong&gt; allows to do is to make our web apps available even when our visitors are not connected to any network (assuming, obviously, that they have visited the website before, under network coverage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is to be said that this feature (called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;AppCache&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;) might not be useful/appropriate for many websites, it still remains a great feature that is going to positively affect the web in the next years, offering a much better user experience and giving a new reason to developers and companies for developing just one great HTML5 web app instead of &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of native applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of the application cache feature can give some benefits to your web app, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;strong&gt;Offline browsing&lt;/strong&gt;: clearly, that is the main advantage&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;strong&gt;Speed&lt;/strong&gt;: Resources are downloaded and therefore faster to load when a user visit your website&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;strong&gt;Less charge to the server&lt;/strong&gt;: as it only have to download resources that have been changed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-8217-s-make-your-website-available-offline:cac56a5fff391b52f21b9921cdfce1eb&#34;&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s make your website available offline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you have to do is to &lt;strong&gt;create a manifest&lt;/strong&gt; that will list all the resources you want the local device to download. This manifest must be declared in your &lt;html&gt; element as an attribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;html manifest=&#34;nameofthemanifest.appcache&#34;&amp;gt;
...
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;.appcache&lt;/em&gt; extension is actually not mandatory, but it&amp;#8217;s the W3C standard, so you better adopt it in order to avoid incompatibilities with strict standard-observing browsers. The manifest attribute in a web application can specify either the relative path of a cache manifest file or an absolute URL (but they must be from the same origin as the application).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s important to know that this manifest must be &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;included in each and every page that you want to be cached&lt;/span&gt;, and you don&amp;#8217;t have to list those pages in the manifest, because they will be automatically saved as the user visit them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cache manifest file must be served with the MIME type text/cache-manifest. In Apache, you can do that adding the following line to your .htaccess file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;AddType text/cache-manifest .appcache&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-appcache-manifest-file:cac56a5fff391b52f21b9921cdfce1eb&#34;&gt;The Appcache manifest file&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Appcache manifest file is a simple text file that lists the resources (identified by URI) that you want the browser to cache for offline access. The following is an example of a manifest file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;CACHE MANIFEST
# mywebapp.appcache v1
# this is my cache manifest 
fileindex.html
cache.html
style.css
image1.png

# Use from network if available
NETWORK:
network.html

# Fallback content
FALLBACK:
/ fallback.html&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s vital for the cache manifest to be identified as such to have &lt;strong&gt;CACHE MANIFEST&lt;/strong&gt; as its first line. All the resources listed after that line are going to be cached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;NETWORK&lt;/strong&gt; section lists all the resources for which a network coverage is required, and you don&amp;#8217;t want the browser to save them and use the cached version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;FALLBACK&lt;/strong&gt; section we&amp;#8217;re going to list the pages that should be showed when a certain resource is not available. In our case, we decided to show &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;fallback.html&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; for every resource not available (&amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;/&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also add a further section &lt;strong&gt;CACHE&lt;/strong&gt;, which will work just as the lines after CACHE MANIFEST. All the three sections CACHE, NETWORK and FALLBACK are optional and can be declared more than once in the manifest file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;testing:cac56a5fff391b52f21b9921cdfce1eb&#34;&gt;Testing!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that this is going to work at the first attempt you&amp;#8217;re probably crazy. The smallest error in the appcache manifest file will actually prevent your application to be locally cached on a device. In such situations, tools like &lt;strong&gt;Manifesto&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a title=&#34;Manifesto&#34; href=&#34;http://manifesto.ericdelabar.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://manifesto.ericdelabar.com/&#34;&gt;http://manifesto.ericdelabar.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) are simply priceless and save you a lot of time and headaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Firefox and a few other browsers display a &lt;strong&gt;notification bar&lt;/strong&gt; the first time a user loads an application that uses the application cache.&lt;/del&gt; [&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt;  Since v. 26, there is no longer a notification bar on Firefox when websites use &lt;em&gt;appcache&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also:cac56a5fff391b52f21b9921cdfce1eb&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A beginner&amp;#8217;s Guide to Using the Application Cache from HTML5Rocks: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/appcache/beginner/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/appcache/beginner/&#34;&gt;http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/appcache/beginner/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check browser compatibilities on HTML5Test: &lt;a href=&#34;http://html5test.com/compare/feature/offline-applicationCache.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://html5test.com/compare/feature/offline-applicationCache.html&#34;&gt;http://html5test.com/compare/feature/offline-applicationCache.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up a full web server on a Raspberry PI</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-web-server-on-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-web-server-on-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to show you how to set up a fully operative &lt;strong&gt;web server&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/2013/01/i-got-a-rasperry-pi/&#34; title=&#34;I got a Rasperry PI!&#34;&gt;Raspberry PI&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically, this a LAMP server, which means Linux+Apache+MySQL+PHP, which the most common combination you find in most of the servers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;refresh-all-your-packages:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Refresh all your packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before we start, it is indicated to &lt;em&gt;refresh all your repositories&lt;/em&gt;, in order to get the most updated version of every software we are going to install. To do that, simply type the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;lang:sh decode:true &#34; &gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apache-web-server:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Apache web server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;&#34;&gt;sudo apt-get install apache2&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this, you have installed now the &lt;a title=&#34;Apache&#34; href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CDQQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fhttpd.apache.org%2F&amp;ei=HTH3UJ7EFqrx4QSohoGABg&amp;usg=AFQjCNGyImC8Qi-rx_Bxd9knbUGKMxH5TQ&amp;sig2=HrOuBOkg6T4w_1_LlDW4cw&amp;bvm=bv.41018144,d.bGE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt; web server on your Raspberry PI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mysql:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install &lt;a title=&#34;MySQL&#34; href=&#34;http://www.mysql.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt;, the Oracle-developed world&amp;#8217;s most famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CDQQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FRelational_database_management_system&amp;ei=2TD3UNzMFu314QSPo4GYBg&amp;usg=AFQjCNF1cHWqW6UJUS3UPBCQCzEG_mHyWQ&amp;sig2=gWQZ0HLHKXEvipfHBL1Cjw&amp;bvm=bv.41018144,d.bGE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RDBMS&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install mysql-server&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php5:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;PHP5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to view your &lt;a title=&#34;PHP&#34; href=&#34;http://www.php.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PHP&lt;/a&gt; made websites, you will have to install PHP5, typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install php5&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install php5-mysql&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second line will install the libraries that make PHP5 able to connect to the MySQL database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ready-to-go:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Ready to go!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your web server is now ready and working, and you can test it by visiting (from a browser) &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/&#34;&gt;http://localhost/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. You can place all your websites&amp;#8217; folders and files at the following path: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;/var/www/html/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-with-mysql:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Working with MySQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will most probably need to work with one or more database, you may want to use a web interface for that. &lt;a title=&#34;Adminer&#34; href=&#34;http://www.adminer.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Adminer&lt;/a&gt; is a great, lightweight and very fast database management tool. To use it, simply type the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;lang:sh decode:true &#34; &gt;cd /var/www
mkdir adminer
cd adminer
sudo wget http://www.adminer.org/latest-mysql-en.php
mv latest-mysql-en.php index.php&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you try to visit &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/adminer&#34;&gt;http://localhost/adminer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; from a browser, you should see your database management interface. To access it, simply insert the MySQL username and password you chose while installing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;In alternative, if you don&amp;#8217;t like Adminer&amp;#8217;s very simple interface and you want a much more graphical and powerful UI, you should give a try to &lt;a title=&#34;Chive&#34; href=&#34;http://www.chive-project.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chive&lt;/a&gt;, a wonderful database management tool developed with the &lt;a title=&#34;Yii framework&#34; href=&#34;http://www.yiiframework.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yii framework&lt;/a&gt;! Install it by typing:&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;del&gt;cd /var/www
wget -O - http://www.chive-project.com/Download/Redirect|tar -xzp&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Visiting &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/chive&#34;&gt;http://localhost/chive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; you will be able to work with Chive.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Chive&lt;/strong&gt; does not appear to have been updated recently. It is therefore no longer a recommended choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all you need to be fully operative with a webserver running on your Raspberry PI. With very few or no changes, the above guide will also help you to install a LAMP web server on Ubuntu and Debian operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1118921666/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1118921666&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=TQVYISKDEHET47YV&#34;&gt;Raspberry Pi User Guide&lt;/a&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;#038;l=as2&amp;#038;o=1&amp;#038;a=1118921666&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; style=&#34;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&#34; /&gt;by Eben Upton (creator of the Raspberry PI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy a [Raspberry Pi 2 Model B Project Board &amp;#8211; 1GB RAM &amp;#8211; 900 MHz Quad-Core CPU][3]&lt;img src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;#038;l=as2&amp;#038;o=1&amp;#038;a=B00T2U7R7I&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; style=&#34;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00T2U7R7I/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00T2U7R7I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=36F2PY7IV6I63X5X&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00T2U7R7I/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00T2U7R7I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=36F2PY7IV6I63X5X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I got a Rasperry PI!</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/i-got-a-rasperry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/i-got-a-rasperry-pi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, I&amp;#8217;ve got it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; alignright&#34; alt=&#34;Raspberry PI&#34; src=&#34;http://www.userlogos.org/files/logos/xelaiv/Raspberry_Pi_Logo_4.png&#34; width=&#34;203&#34; height=&#34;152&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After more or less 3 weeks of waiting, I can finally put my hands on my new, shiny &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry PI&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;img alt=&#34;Raspberry PI&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/c/cb/Raspberry_Pi_Logo.svg&#34; width=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;  And I have to say I had lose any hope to get it before 2013, but, unexpectedly, it got to my house just a few hours before 2012 came to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Rasp-what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Just in case you have never heard about it (if so, please consider starting to sometimes read at least the &lt;a title=&#34;BBC Tech&#34; href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/technology/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tech section&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BBC news&lt;/a&gt; website, because it is completely unacceptable for a geek not to be aware about the Raspberry PI! :P), the Raspberry PI &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;is a credit-card-sized single-board computer developed in the UK by the Raspberry Pi Foundation with the intention of stimulating the teaching of basic computer science in schools.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; (source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raspberry_Pi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**So, what&amp;#8217;s so great about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** The great thing about the Raspberry PI, is that it is a &lt;em&gt;full Linux PC&lt;/em&gt; (with very low performances, as you might expect) and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;it costs just 35$&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for its Model B-version, which is better equipped (Model A is -in my opinion- simply not enough, without regarding of what you use it for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/2013/01/i-got-a-rasperry-pi/castelfranco-di-sotto-20121231-00196/&#34; rel=&#34;attachment wp-att-61&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-61 alignleft&#34; style=&#34;margin-right: 5px;&#34; alt=&#34;My Rasperry PI (2)&#34; src=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Castelfranco-di-Sotto-20121231-00196-300x225.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Castelfranco-di-Sotto-20121231-00196-300x225.jpg 300w, http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/Castelfranco-di-Sotto-20121231-00196.jpg 1024w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Besides the purpose for which the Raspberry PI is developed, which is to teach kids and young people basic programming skills, there are many things you can do with such a device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main things I see programmers doing with the Raspberry PI is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;playing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Having fun with it, experimenting anything their imagination can produce (as long as that small device can do it &amp;#8211; don&amp;#8217;t forget it is a very small PC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what I am doing with it in these days is to &lt;strong&gt;set up a full LAMP server&lt;/strong&gt;, and I will post in the next days how to do it (it&amp;#8217;s quite simple).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also a few other things I want to try it for, like using it as a &lt;strong&gt;backup server&lt;/strong&gt; (adding to it an external HD), or as a &lt;strong&gt;media centre&lt;/strong&gt; (with the help of &lt;a title=&#34;Raspbmc&#34; href=&#34;http://www.raspbmc.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Raspbmc&lt;/a&gt;). And I am sure new ideas (even for business) about how to use it will come to my mind in the next weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more informations about the Raspberry PI project, just visit the Foundation&amp;#8217;s official website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raspberrypi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raspberrypi.org&#34;&gt;http://www.raspberrypi.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or you can buy a [Raspberry Pi Model B 512 MB RAM Latest VERSION][1] &lt;img style=&#34;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://ir-uk.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi07-21&amp;l=as2&amp;o=2&amp;a=B009SMWSQA&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;for yourself on &lt;strong&gt;Amazon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B009SMWSQA/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B009SMWSQA&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi07-21&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B009SMWSQA/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=6738&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B009SMWSQA&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi07-21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yii: XML generator</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/xml-generator-yii-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/xml-generator-yii-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I needed to create some custom XMLs for a project I am working on, I have created an Yii extension based on a nice class being developed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://simonwillison.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Simon Willison&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this extension, everyone will be easily able to generate an XML. I am pretty sure there may be different and even more powerful approaches to do the same thing, but what I like of this extension is that it does make really simple to create a custom XML. And, sometimes, simple is better -especially when it means less time to do the same thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve never used an extension with the Yii framework, you may find useful to read the &amp;#8216;extensions&amp;#8217; section on the Yii framework official website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yiiframework.com/doc/guide/1.1/en/extension.overview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yiiframework.com/doc/guide/1.1/en/extension.overview&#34;&gt;http://www.yiiframework.com/doc/guide/1.1/en/extension.overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8211; Download the [XmlGenerator]&lt;a href=&#34;extension for Yii framework&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/XmlGenerator1.zip&#34;&gt;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/XmlGenerator1.zip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>