<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in News on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple and the battle for privacy</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/apple-and-the-battle-for-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/apple-and-the-battle-for-privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt; Apple is in no position for attacking other companies over how they deal with their users privacy and security. There is nothing in their policies that makes us think they care about us more than other companies do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a few weeks ago, Apple&amp;#8217;s CEO Tim Cook delivered a &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2015/06/02/apples-tim-cook-delivers-blistering-speech-on-encryption-privacy/#.uvoewi:m2qz&#34;&gt;speech&lt;/a&gt; on privacy, security and how Apple is so much better at these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, someone would say I am an anti-Apple guy, although that&amp;#8217;s demonstrably false, if for nothing else, because I have owned and worked with several Apple devices during the course of the past few years. I do not always enjoy how they market their products, the way they make you feel like you absolutely need something you actually don&amp;#8217;t. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/uk/osx/&#34;&gt;Mac OS&lt;/a&gt; is probably my favourite OS, but it is extremely expensive to buy, and in my opinion, unless you are a professional, you really don&amp;#8217;t need anything more than a nice laptop with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubuntu.com&#34;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; on it. But that&amp;#8217;s besides the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made me feel quite uncomfortable to listen to Cook&amp;#8217;s words on how we can all trust Apple with our data and our messages. Now, don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong, it&amp;#8217;s amazing that a CEO of a major tech company would stand up in defense of his customers&amp;#8217; data, stating how unacceptable it is for any other company not to act this way. But then it made me think that, great words aside, there was nothing there that would justify him attacking other companies (mostly, Google), and positioning himself as the new champion for the defense of people&amp;#8217;s security and privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are actually a few reasons why Apple &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt; in the position of becoming the new advocate of privacy and security:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple has been shown vulnerable to attacks a few times already&lt;/strong&gt;. Just think of the not-too-long-ago leaked &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ibtimes.com/icloud-nude-leaks-26-celebrities-affected-nude-photo-scandal-1692540&#34;&gt;celebrity pictures&lt;/a&gt; from iCloud. Of course, these things happen, not only to Apple products, and most of the times it&amp;#8217;s just people&amp;#8217;s fault for not creating stronger passwords/enabling &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-factor_authentication&#34;&gt;two-factor authentication&lt;/a&gt;. But still, we can&amp;#8217;t recall anything like that happening with Gmail, or Google+ Photos in recent times. And even it had, it would only show they are all susceptible to such attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They are a very closed company&lt;/strong&gt; From my point of view, this is a major one. If the CEO of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redhat.com&#34;&gt;Red Hat&lt;/a&gt; were to give a similar speech, I would have applauded him. Why? Because Red Hat (like some other companies out there) adheres to a strict policy of transparency, which is very clear first and foremost by the fact that they open source &lt;strong&gt;all of their products&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that they could never put themselves in Cook&amp;#8217;s position without having thousands of people going to actually check their code to verify the truth of their claims. But this is simply impossible with Apple. A more closed, walled-garden type of company I can&amp;#8217;t think of. A while ago my wife and I had a really bad experience with trying to move all our iCloud photos somewhere else, so that we could access them from our non-Apple devices as well. We struggled and struggled, and took us hours to move everything. The reality is, there is no easy way to opt-out from Apple, whereas it&amp;#8217;s really easy to move away from most of, say, Google&amp;#8217;s products. If they really cared about my data, they should at least give me the ability to easily export it somewhere else anytime I want. It is my data, after all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is not true that if something is for free, then you must be the real product&lt;/strong&gt;. Derek Powazek wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://powazek.com/posts/3229&#34;&gt;great piece&lt;/a&gt; on this. Companies like Apple like to charge you for everything. And they want to make you believe that because you are paying &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of money, you will have a better service and your data won&amp;#8217;t be used for other purposes, like, showing you ads based on your searches. But this is demonstrably false. First of all, there is no direct connection between you paying for a service and how your data will be used. For all we know, Apple (and others) could be doing &lt;a href=&#34;http://advertising.apple.com/&#34;&gt;the same thing&lt;/a&gt; with your data even though you paid for their products. Besides, I can give you plenty of examples of products for which I have paid money, only to be treated rubbish by the companies who made them. On the other hand, some of the free services that I use, have made me incredibly happy. All this is saying, is that &lt;em&gt;there is no correlation between how much you pay, and how much they care about you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said at the beginning, I am not an anti-Apple person, and I didn&amp;#8217;t write this piece to attack Apple. Rather, I wanted to put things back into the right perspective. I do not believe companies like Google, Microsoft or Amazon do any better than Apple in terms of privacy and security. Which doesn&amp;#8217;t mean what they do is bad. All of these companies adopt (or are in the process to adopt) first-class encryption techniques, and one would want to argue that if there is anyone with enough resources to actually keep your data safe, then it has to be these companies, including Apple. Besides, privacy is a highly regulated matter (especially here in [Europe][9]), and so there is no way they can use your data to do what they want, unless you explicitly authorise them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it would be arrogant of one of them to stand up as the messiah of privacy and security, especially if that means attacking other companies. If they want us to keep trusting them with our data, they need to keep doing the right thing. They should ask us only for informations that are strictly necessary; they should use world class encryption and spare no resource in order to keep everything safe; they should use all their influence when governments try to change laws and make it acceptable for them to have a look at my holidays pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Cover photo from Flickr.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_Protection_Directive&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_Protection_Directive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hailo and their “Journey into Microservices”</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago, while looking for experiences of companies actually transitioning into a Microservice architecture, I stumbled upon this nicely written, real-world series of articles from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mattheath&#34;&gt;Matt Heath&lt;/a&gt;, published on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hailoapp.com&#34;&gt;Hailo&lt;/a&gt; tech blog. The articles talk about their moving from a mostly-PHP, monolithic architecture, towards one based on Microservices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very interesting to read about the challenges of a company that started that everyone else, and then had to face the inevitable problems of scalability and code maintainability. It is also stimulating to see how they answered the questions almost everyone asks when trying to move into a Microservices architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, read the articles, starting from the first one: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-1/&#34;&gt;A Journey into Microservices&lt;/a&gt;, and then go ahead with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-2/&#34;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-3/&#34;&gt;part three&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question: have you worked on a transition to a microservice architecture? What has your experience been? Share your thoughts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or [Twitter][7].&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Featured photo from the Hailo website&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/MB66xW&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/MB66xW&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to Germany!</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/moving-to-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/moving-to-germany/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And so here we are. After less than a year of marriage, my wife and I are relocating to a new Country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been living in Milan, Italy since we got married, and, I will admit, we have loved the city. Milan is, as I often say, the Italian idea of what a metropolis would be. While it has all the characteristics of a modern European city, it is also very, very Italian. It is a city definitely worth visiting and a lovely place to work and live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from September the 1st I am going to be working in Berlin, Germany for a very big international IT company that has its headquarters in the German capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are absolutely thrilled by this new opportunity and we had actually been looking at going to live in a bigger European city for a while, so this job opportunity does indeed come as a sort of &amp;#8216;answer&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be working with lots of extremely skilled professionals, which makes the whole thing very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Berlin does look like an impressively dynamic city, with many creative people and a start up culture that is probably second to none in Europe. And somehow I find the German culture quite fascinating, so I am happy that I&amp;#8217;ll be able to learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Germany, here we come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: if you happen to come to Berlin in the next months and you have anything interesting to share, feel free to drop me a line and I will be happy to have a coffee with you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing for Milk &amp; Honey Mag</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/writing-for-milk-honey-mag/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/writing-for-milk-honey-mag/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently written a couple of articles for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.milkandhoneymag.com&#34;&gt;Milk &amp;amp; Honey Mag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a lifestyle magazine for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.milkandhoneymag.com&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-199 alignright&#34; alt=&#34;Milk &amp; Honey Mag&#34; src=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/mh_screenshot-300x161.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;161&#34; srcset=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/mh_screenshot-300x161.png 300w, http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/mh_screenshot-1024x551.png 1024w&#34; sizes=&#34;(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The articles that I have written for them so far are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://milkandhoneymag.com/2014/02/22/chromebook-from-google-smaller-than-a-laptop-more-useful-than-a-tablet/&#34;&gt;Chromebook from Google: smaller than a laptop, more useful than a tablet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I try to give an overview of what a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/intl/it/chrome/devices/hp-chromebook-11/#hp-cb-11-everyday&amp;amp;tab=colour-blue&amp;amp;tab=app-maps&#34;&gt;Chromebook&lt;/a&gt; is, and what are the differences between it and the devices that everyone already knows (laptops, tablets, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am addressing an audience composed mostly by women, I am also focussing on the &amp;#8220;cool factor&amp;#8221;, as it seems to me that for a tech product to succeed, having the best combination of software and hardware put together is just not enough; for a product to become a must-have, a great design and a solid, recognisable brand are also necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://milkandhoneymag.com/2014/02/02/scribd-like-netflix-for-ebook/&#34;&gt;Scribd is like Netflix for ebooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick introduction and overview of [Scribd][5], a new, interesting service that allows you to read millions of ebooks just by paying a small monthly subscription.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you will enjoy reading these articles. Let me know what do you think about them, I&amp;#8217;d be more than happy to hear from you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE (1st July 2014): Milk &amp;amp; Honey Mag is currently under mantainance and will be launched in a completely new format in the next weeks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd UPDATE (January 2015): Milk &amp;amp; Honey Mag is not going to be relaunched as we knew it before.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scribd.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.scribd.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>