<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Php on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/php/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Php on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/php/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hailo and their “Journey into Microservices”</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago, while looking for experiences of companies actually transitioning into a Microservice architecture, I stumbled upon this nicely written, real-world series of articles from &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mattheath&#34;&gt;Matt Heath&lt;/a&gt;, published on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hailoapp.com&#34;&gt;Hailo&lt;/a&gt; tech blog. The articles talk about their moving from a mostly-PHP, monolithic architecture, towards one based on Microservices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very interesting to read about the challenges of a company that started that everyone else, and then had to face the inevitable problems of scalability and code maintainability. It is also stimulating to see how they answered the questions almost everyone asks when trying to move into a Microservices architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, read the articles, starting from the first one: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-1/&#34;&gt;A Journey into Microservices&lt;/a&gt;, and then go ahead with &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-2/&#34;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sudo.hailoapp.com/services/2015/03/09/journey-into-a-microservice-world-part-3/&#34;&gt;part three&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question: have you worked on a transition to a microservice architecture? What has your experience been? Share your thoughts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or [Twitter][7].&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Featured photo from the Hailo website&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/MB66xW&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/hailo-journey-into-microservices/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/MB66xW&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example of a Microservice</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/an-example-of-a-microservice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/an-example-of-a-microservice/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After writing on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/micro-services-a-quick-introduction/&#34;&gt;Microservices&lt;/a&gt;, I received a few feedbacks from people who found the topic fascinating but struggled to see how to effectively apply it in reality. So I decided to develop a little microservice, to use as a practical example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introducing-microtranslator:e46d2f865b53e2e53becb431606efa7c&#34;&gt;Introducing MicroTranslator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/marcotroisi/microtranslator&#34;&gt;MicroTranslator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a microservice that I have built, which is supposed to handle locale and translations in an application. Its tech stack is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP &amp;gt;= 5.4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fatfreeframework.com&#34;&gt;Fat Free framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mossphp/moss-locale&#34;&gt;Moss Locale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mongodb.com&#34;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del datetime=&#34;2015-07-20T07:04:33+00:00&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; at the time of this writing (14 Apr &amp;#8217;15) I am still working on MicroTranslator. It will be production-ready (documentation included) in a few days. Sorry about that!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-comes-with-rest-api:e46d2f865b53e2e53becb431606efa7c&#34;&gt;It comes with REST API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MicroTranslator provides simple-to-use REST API. For this reason, you need to know little to no PHP to use it. Simply fire up an instance of PHP on whatever machine you like, and then use the APIs to get the translations on the other Microservices that compose your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is important, in my opinion. It means that you can quickly begin working on your application without having to focus on a tedious task such as handling translations, but also that, at any point in time, you can completely get rid of it and rewrite it with, perhaps, a faster language. Or you can simply upgrade your hardware and keep relying on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;8220-i-could-have-done-this-myself-8221:e46d2f865b53e2e53becb431606efa7c&#34;&gt;&amp;#8220;I could have done this myself&amp;#8221;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may think now, &amp;#8220;why should I use your stuff when I can write my own translation manager, using the tools that I like the most?&amp;#8221; The simple answer here is &amp;#8220;You shouldn&amp;#8217;t (use my translation manager)!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I would also like to point out that, unless translations represent the core of your application, there is no reason why you would want to waste your time rewriting a library that does the same thing. But even if you do, what you should be avoiding is to tie it all up with the rest of your application. Using a Microservices architecture will allow you to &lt;em&gt;replace&lt;/em&gt; parts of your application quickly and seamlessly. And, it will give you the power of choosing the right tools, framework, database, etc for the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-by-point:e46d2f865b53e2e53becb431606efa7c&#34;&gt;Point by point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, one of the reasons why I worked on MicroTranslator is because I wanted to create a real-life example out of my previous article on &lt;em&gt;what is a Microservice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s have a look at the points I outlined back then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is a Stand-alone service/application.&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes, MicroTranslator is stand-alone. It doesn&amp;#8217;t need, and actually, it doesn&amp;#8217;t want, to be included into your PHP application. You can connect to it, get and send to it all the data that you need, but you will not find MicroTranslator-specific code in your application. Just generic API calls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is quick to (re)write.&lt;/strong&gt;: Absolutely! I wrote MicroTranslator in a weekend plus a few other free hours during the week. You can totally rewrite it in a week or less as soon as you feel like it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It focuses on one task&lt;/strong&gt;: It only cares about your translations. It doesn&amp;#8217;t even want to know how you use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is Language-agnostic.&lt;/strong&gt;: Well, MicroTranslator is clearly written in PHP, but you can use its APIs from application, regardless of the language/framework/tools you are using.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is aware of failures&lt;/strong&gt;. This clearly depends on the rest of the application. But, for example, you can cache the translations that you get from MicroTranslator, so that, should it be unreachable at a certain point in time, you can still handle the situation graciously. One thing is sure: if MicroTranslator goes down, it won&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; affect your main application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-practice-it-8217-s-not-that-difficult:e46d2f865b53e2e53becb431606efa7c&#34;&gt;In practice, it&amp;#8217;s not that difficult&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s amazing how simple things can look like when we see them in real-life examples. In fact, despite the buzzword-mania and all the hype around Microservices, something that we often fail to understand is how simple they are. Building a Microservice is as simple as a few days of work. Building an entire application based on a Microservices Architecture is as simple as being able to separate everything into small services/applications that are only concerned about one little thing, and they do that &lt;em&gt;very well&lt;/em&gt;. This is, by the way, also one the keys of greater &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/productive-programmer-5-tips/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question: have you already tried to build a Microservice, or even an entire application based on a Microservices architecture? I would love to have a look and learn from you as well. Share your work on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=http://www.marcotroisi.com/an-example-of-a-microservice/&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/an-example-of-a-microservice/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/KdOum9&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Two Cents on Go</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/my-two-cents-on-golang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/my-two-cents-on-golang/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been recently studying and trying &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.golang.org&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; (Golang), a statically typed language developed by Google, which promises really fast execution times and a pleasant development experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must say, it is pleasant to use indeed. And quite simple to learn. But it does also demolish some of the things that, coming from other languages, you might be giving for granted. While trying to get my head around it, it felt a lot like when I was trying to learn proper Javascript (i.e. &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; jQuery), that is, it can sometimes take a while to understand, but then at one point something &amp;#8216;clicks&amp;#8217;, and immediately everything becomes so clear and easy. You do not end up necessarily thinking that it is &lt;em&gt;the best language ever&lt;/em&gt;, but you do come to appreciate its design choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is easy to use, no doubt about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just for the sake of fun, I was inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://avelino.xxx/2014/03/golang-c-and-python-the-benchmark-time&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Thiago Avelino to try doing the same benchmark comparison between PHP and Go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does it feel so easy and natural to &amp;#8216;&lt;em&gt;port&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8216; code from PHP to Go, but the difference in terms of execution times is quite remarkable (granted, this is a very simple test, and I do not need to tell you that you should not base your choice of a programming language on it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the following is the script in PHP:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;?php
function fact($n){
    if($n===0)return 1;
    return $n*fact($n-1);
}

function calc(){
    $t = 0;
    for($i=0; $i&amp;lt;100000; $i++){
        for($j=0; $j&amp;lt;8; $j++){
            $t += fact($j);
        }
    }
    return $t;
}

$result = calc();
echo $result.&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and this is the result of the benchmark:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;time php factorial.php
591400000

real    0m0.658s
user    0m0.488s
sys 0m0.004s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following, instead, is the Go code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;package main

import &amp;quot;fmt&amp;quot;

func main() {

    result := calc()
    fmt.Println(result)
}

func fact(n int) int {
    if n == 0 {
        return 1
    }

    return n * fact(n-1)
}

func calc() int {
    t := 0
    for i := 0; i &amp;lt; 100000; i++ {
        for j := 0; j &amp;lt; 8; j++ {
            t += fact(j)
        }
    }

    return t
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and here is the benchmark result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;time go run factorial.go
591400000

real    0m0.156s
user    0m0.138s
sys 0m0.021s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go is remarkably faster, while being frankly pretty easy to write. I have come to appreciate this language more and more, and I would wholeheartedly suggest to any PHP/Ruby/Python developer to add this nice, simple and fast language to his own skills. Learning more programming languages always ultimately make you a better developer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WordPress and Ghost: a CMS vs a blogging platform</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/wordpress-and-ghost/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/wordpress-and-ghost/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am definitely amongst the growing group of developers that are fascinated and thrilled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nodejs.org&#34;&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;, its thriving community, its being simple yet powerful, super-fast and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my main language remains &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.php.net&#34;&gt;PHP&lt;/a&gt; (mostly because my employer wants me to work with it, but also because of its enormous libraries collection and its maturity as a language for the web), I can undoubtedly see a future with most of the cool apps out there being developed with node.js. I am convinced that, should I start a new project of my own today, a project that I believed would conquer the market, I would totally go for a lightweight HTML5 + CSS3 + JS (with the help of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.angularjs.org&#34;&gt;Angular.js&lt;/a&gt;) interface backed by a powerful node.js (with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.expressjs.com&#34;&gt;express.js&lt;/a&gt;)-based API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I came to know about this new, elegant and lightweight blogging platform named &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ghost.org&#34;&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; and based on node.js I was more than happy and I thought it was just what we needed to be &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; set free from WordPress! But I then worked out that I was almost surely wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wordpress-is-a-cms-not-a-blogging-platform:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;WordPress is a CMS, not a blogging platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it still remains the best blogging platform out there, as of today &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordpress.org&#34;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; is a fully fledged CMS and, in my opinion, it&amp;#8217;s the best CMS you might desire. It&amp;#8217;s simple enough to use and it&amp;#8217;s got so many &lt;a href=&#34;http://wordpress.org/plugins/&#34;&gt;plugins and extensions&lt;/a&gt; that to call it an ecosystem wouldn&amp;#8217;t mean overrating it. And, to be fair, the fact that it&amp;#8217;s based on PHP means that it can run virtually everywhere with the minimum effort required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ghost-is-what-it-claims-to-be-just-a-blogging-platform:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;Ghost is what it claims to be: &lt;em&gt;just a blogging platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost is beautiful, easy to use and it&amp;#8217;s got everything in the right place. The dashboard is right the one that you would love to have in your WordPress blog. And it&amp;#8217;s seriously fast, and you would expect that since it&amp;#8217;s built on node.js. But it&amp;#8217;s limited to blogging and they ([the developers][8]) want it to be so. That&amp;#8217;s great indeed, but it means that you have to be sure that your blog will always be just a blog, nothing more. And you&amp;#8217;ve got to know that, apart from the pleasure of a great platform for writing, you&amp;#8217;re not going to have a lot more in terms of functionalities and extensions. Of course they&amp;#8217;ll come in the future, but we can easily say that in the foreseeable future they won&amp;#8217;t be as many as WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-verdict:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;Conclusion/Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#8217;re both great platforms, WordPress being a lot more mature, Ghost being still in its infancy. Just don&amp;#8217;t think of them as one replacing the other. They do different things, and they both work. Decide &lt;em&gt;what your website is gonna be about&lt;/em&gt; and then pick the right platform for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ghost.org/about/&#34;&gt;https://ghost.org/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up a full web server on a Raspberry PI</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-web-server-on-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/how-to-web-server-on-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to show you how to set up a fully operative &lt;strong&gt;web server&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/2013/01/i-got-a-rasperry-pi/&#34; title=&#34;I got a Rasperry PI!&#34;&gt;Raspberry PI&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically, this a LAMP server, which means Linux+Apache+MySQL+PHP, which the most common combination you find in most of the servers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;refresh-all-your-packages:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Refresh all your packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before we start, it is indicated to &lt;em&gt;refresh all your repositories&lt;/em&gt;, in order to get the most updated version of every software we are going to install. To do that, simply type the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;lang:sh decode:true &#34; &gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apache-web-server:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Apache web server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;&#34;&gt;sudo apt-get install apache2&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this, you have installed now the &lt;a title=&#34;Apache&#34; href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CDQQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fhttpd.apache.org%2F&amp;ei=HTH3UJ7EFqrx4QSohoGABg&amp;usg=AFQjCNGyImC8Qi-rx_Bxd9knbUGKMxH5TQ&amp;sig2=HrOuBOkg6T4w_1_LlDW4cw&amp;bvm=bv.41018144,d.bGE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Apache&lt;/a&gt; web server on your Raspberry PI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mysql:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install &lt;a title=&#34;MySQL&#34; href=&#34;http://www.mysql.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt;, the Oracle-developed world&amp;#8217;s most famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CDQQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FRelational_database_management_system&amp;ei=2TD3UNzMFu314QSPo4GYBg&amp;usg=AFQjCNF1cHWqW6UJUS3UPBCQCzEG_mHyWQ&amp;sig2=gWQZ0HLHKXEvipfHBL1Cjw&amp;bvm=bv.41018144,d.bGE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RDBMS&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install mysql-server&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php5:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;PHP5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to view your &lt;a title=&#34;PHP&#34; href=&#34;http://www.php.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PHP&lt;/a&gt; made websites, you will have to install PHP5, typing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install php5&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install php5-mysql&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second line will install the libraries that make PHP5 able to connect to the MySQL database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ready-to-go:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Ready to go!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your web server is now ready and working, and you can test it by visiting (from a browser) &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/&#34;&gt;http://localhost/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. You can place all your websites&amp;#8217; folders and files at the following path: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;/var/www/html/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-with-mysql:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Working with MySQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will most probably need to work with one or more database, you may want to use a web interface for that. &lt;a title=&#34;Adminer&#34; href=&#34;http://www.adminer.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Adminer&lt;/a&gt; is a great, lightweight and very fast database management tool. To use it, simply type the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;lang:sh decode:true &#34; &gt;cd /var/www
mkdir adminer
cd adminer
sudo wget http://www.adminer.org/latest-mysql-en.php
mv latest-mysql-en.php index.php&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you try to visit &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/adminer&#34;&gt;http://localhost/adminer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; from a browser, you should see your database management interface. To access it, simply insert the MySQL username and password you chose while installing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;In alternative, if you don&amp;#8217;t like Adminer&amp;#8217;s very simple interface and you want a much more graphical and powerful UI, you should give a try to &lt;a title=&#34;Chive&#34; href=&#34;http://www.chive-project.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Chive&lt;/a&gt;, a wonderful database management tool developed with the &lt;a title=&#34;Yii framework&#34; href=&#34;http://www.yiiframework.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yii framework&lt;/a&gt;! Install it by typing:&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;del&gt;cd /var/www
wget -O - http://www.chive-project.com/Download/Redirect|tar -xzp&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Visiting &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost/chive&#34;&gt;http://localhost/chive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; you will be able to work with Chive.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Chive&lt;/strong&gt; does not appear to have been updated recently. It is therefore no longer a recommended choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all you need to be fully operative with a webserver running on your Raspberry PI. With very few or no changes, the above guide will also help you to install a LAMP web server on Ubuntu and Debian operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also:5c5e63888e4336f3800a8a64c97cb254&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1118921666/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1118921666&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=TQVYISKDEHET47YV&#34;&gt;Raspberry Pi User Guide&lt;/a&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;#038;l=as2&amp;#038;o=1&amp;#038;a=1118921666&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; style=&#34;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&#34; /&gt;by Eben Upton (creator of the Raspberry PI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy a [Raspberry Pi 2 Model B Project Board &amp;#8211; 1GB RAM &amp;#8211; 900 MHz Quad-Core CPU][3]&lt;img src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;#038;l=as2&amp;#038;o=1&amp;#038;a=B00T2U7R7I&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; style=&#34;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00T2U7R7I/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00T2U7R7I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=36F2PY7IV6I63X5X&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00T2U7R7I/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00T2U7R7I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=36F2PY7IV6I63X5X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>