<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ghost on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/ghost/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ghost on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/tags/ghost/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What would your ideal Publishing Platform look like?</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/what-would-your-ideal-publishing-platform-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/what-would-your-ideal-publishing-platform-look-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been struggling for a while with finding the right CMS and/or publishing platform. All of them seem to have good parts and less good parts, and that is okay. In a (possible, potential) future attempt of myself to try building the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; publishing platform, I have decided to list some of the things that it seems to me people would usually look for in a CMS or a blogging platform. I would like as many people as possible to select in the poll below what are the things that would make them choose a publishing platform over another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this will result, one day, in the publishing platform that we all have always dreamed of!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;polls-2&#34; class=&#34;wp-polls&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;polls-2-loading&#34; class=&#34;wp-polls-loading&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/plugins/wp-polls/images/loading.gif&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; alt=&#34;Loading ...&#34; title=&#34;Loading ...&#34; class=&#34;wp-polls-image&#34; /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Loading ...
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WordPress and Ghost: a CMS vs a blogging platform</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/wordpress-and-ghost/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/wordpress-and-ghost/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am definitely amongst the growing group of developers that are fascinated and thrilled by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nodejs.org&#34;&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;, its thriving community, its being simple yet powerful, super-fast and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my main language remains &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.php.net&#34;&gt;PHP&lt;/a&gt; (mostly because my employer wants me to work with it, but also because of its enormous libraries collection and its maturity as a language for the web), I can undoubtedly see a future with most of the cool apps out there being developed with node.js. I am convinced that, should I start a new project of my own today, a project that I believed would conquer the market, I would totally go for a lightweight HTML5 + CSS3 + JS (with the help of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.angularjs.org&#34;&gt;Angular.js&lt;/a&gt;) interface backed by a powerful node.js (with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.expressjs.com&#34;&gt;express.js&lt;/a&gt;)-based API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I came to know about this new, elegant and lightweight blogging platform named &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ghost.org&#34;&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; and based on node.js I was more than happy and I thought it was just what we needed to be &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; set free from WordPress! But I then worked out that I was almost surely wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wordpress-is-a-cms-not-a-blogging-platform:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;WordPress is a CMS, not a blogging platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it still remains the best blogging platform out there, as of today &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordpress.org&#34;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; is a fully fledged CMS and, in my opinion, it&amp;#8217;s the best CMS you might desire. It&amp;#8217;s simple enough to use and it&amp;#8217;s got so many &lt;a href=&#34;http://wordpress.org/plugins/&#34;&gt;plugins and extensions&lt;/a&gt; that to call it an ecosystem wouldn&amp;#8217;t mean overrating it. And, to be fair, the fact that it&amp;#8217;s based on PHP means that it can run virtually everywhere with the minimum effort required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ghost-is-what-it-claims-to-be-just-a-blogging-platform:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;Ghost is what it claims to be: &lt;em&gt;just a blogging platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost is beautiful, easy to use and it&amp;#8217;s got everything in the right place. The dashboard is right the one that you would love to have in your WordPress blog. And it&amp;#8217;s seriously fast, and you would expect that since it&amp;#8217;s built on node.js. But it&amp;#8217;s limited to blogging and they ([the developers][8]) want it to be so. That&amp;#8217;s great indeed, but it means that you have to be sure that your blog will always be just a blog, nothing more. And you&amp;#8217;ve got to know that, apart from the pleasure of a great platform for writing, you&amp;#8217;re not going to have a lot more in terms of functionalities and extensions. Of course they&amp;#8217;ll come in the future, but we can easily say that in the foreseeable future they won&amp;#8217;t be as many as WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-verdict:e98746c1693166ee1e473de41c4d5de5&#34;&gt;Conclusion/Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#8217;re both great platforms, WordPress being a lot more mature, Ghost being still in its infancy. Just don&amp;#8217;t think of them as one replacing the other. They do different things, and they both work. Decide &lt;em&gt;what your website is gonna be about&lt;/em&gt; and then pick the right platform for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ghost.org/about/&#34;&gt;https://ghost.org/about/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>