<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About-rsses on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>https://www.marcotroisi.com/about/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in About-rsses on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>Marco Troisi</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.marcotroisi.com/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://www.marcotroisi.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.marcotroisi.com/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hello! 👋&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working in tech for almost 15 years, taking on various roles such as Software Engineer, Tech Lead, Cloud Architect, CTO, and Cloud Consultant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve designed cloud solutions, led teams, and developed a lot of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gained valuable experience at companies like Rocket Internet, ServisBOT, and Trilo. I enjoy the structure of big companies but am truly passionate about the energy and creativity found in startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I specialise in serverless architectures within the AWS cloud, a field where I&amp;rsquo;ve dedicated over 7 years of my career. This specialisation is not just my work; it&amp;rsquo;s my craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away from the keyboard, I march to the beat of a different drum—quite literally. As a former drummer in a prog-rock band, I understand rhythm, whether in music or code. I start my day by making a cup of specialty coffee using my V60, which is a thoughtful process for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an insatiable reader with a penchant for the profound and the thrilling, delving into the realms of philosophy, history, religion, and the occasional spy novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that life is a continuous learning process, and I bring this ethos into every project I undertake. Let&amp;rsquo;s connect and create something remarkable together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to meet up and have a chat, discuss a project or ask me for help, please do not hesitate to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marcotroisi.com/contact/&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;contact-info-marcotroisi-com&#34;&gt;Contact (info@marcotroisi.com)&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>