<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</title>
    <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on Marco Troisi | technology, software development and productivity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.marcotroisi.com/categories/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What can we learn from Periscope</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/what-can-we-learn-from-periscope/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/what-can-we-learn-from-periscope/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.periscope.tv&#34;&gt;Periscope&lt;/a&gt; for a while now, and I am really enjoying it. If you don&amp;#8217;t know it, Periscope is Twitter&amp;#8217;s new live streaming app, that allows anyone to stream directly from one&amp;#8217;s smartphone, and it will notify you as soon as someone you follow is live-streaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of live streaming is not a new one, but Periscope (alongside with their competitor, &lt;a href=&#34;https://meerkatapp.co/&#34;&gt;Meerkat&lt;/a&gt;) has made it really easy to do so from a mobile device and, most importantly, to create a community of followers around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are on Twitter, it makes sense that you&amp;#8217;d want to give Periscope a shot. What makes it different from YouTube is of course the live element, what makes it different from, say, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/hangouts/onair&#34;&gt;Google Hangouts On Air&lt;/a&gt;, is the sense of &lt;em&gt;impromptu-ness&lt;/em&gt; and familiarity that it creates, as you&amp;#8217;re literally speaking from your phone, but also the fact that you already have a community of followers that will be notified when you start streaming, so there is no need to plan it in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I have been using Periscope as a watcher, rather than a streamer, in order to follow some of my favourite people that I already follow on other social media channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-8217-s-great-about-periscope:506996eb1ee3dc44d275f124525b4fee&#34;&gt;What&amp;#8217;s great about Periscope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright wp-image-446 size-full&#34; src=&#34;http://www.marcotroisi.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/periscope.png&#34; alt=&#34;periscope&#34; width=&#34;228&#34; height=&#34;228&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you use Periscope, two things will become obvious to you after a little while:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app is beautifully designed. It&amp;#8217;s elegant yet simple to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is still a lot that can be improved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this great, and I think there is something engineers, product managers and other people involved in building apps and online services can learn. It&amp;#8217;s something that has to do with focus, with avoiding being a perfectionist and with not wasting time. Here&amp;#8217;s what I think are the lesson Periscope&amp;#8217;s creators can teach us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core business&lt;/strong&gt;. Spend some time understanding what exactly your core business is about, and focus mainly on that until you know it&amp;#8217;s absolutely awesome. In Periscope&amp;#8217;s case the core business is &lt;em&gt;live streaming&lt;/em&gt;. There is much more they can do to make the app better and better, like a better player for re-watching videos, a landscape mode, perhaps even a web/desktop version of the app. But, the things that are there, are absolutely great. The app does only a few things, but it works so well! It&amp;#8217;s smooth, it&amp;#8217;s elegant, it&amp;#8217;s simple. In other words, it&amp;#8217;s addictive. Just like Twitter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perfectionism is bad&lt;/strong&gt;. Saying that you want your app to be great is one thing. Trying to make it perfect is unrealistic. Once you&amp;#8217;ve found your core business, make sure you deliver enough functionalities so that users can actually understand, and enjoy, the core business. When you use Periscope, it won&amp;#8217;t take you long before realising that the app is all about live streaming and creating a community around live videos. That&amp;#8217;s it. Like I said, there are so many functionalities they could add, but trying to have them all from the start, would have delayed indefinitely their launch, and would have probably confused people on what the app is about. Think of Google and their years-long beta version of Gmail: they kept it in beta knowing that they wanted to keep improving it. Yet, the core functionalities where there, and, frankly, they were great from the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t waste time&lt;/strong&gt;. In the programming world, we talk about &lt;em&gt;premature optimisation&lt;/em&gt; as the unfortunate situation where programmers spend too much time thinking about how to make sure the app is ready for a lot of functionalities that, from a business point of view, may not even have been decided yet. The solution to that, is to develop software that has a solid foundation, and that is flexible enough that you can keep improving it and adding to it without fear of breaking something in the process. Periscope seems to have done this. Since I have been using it, I have experienced no crashes. The app works really well and it seems to me to be pretty stable. Yet, as I have already said, there are things they could add to make it better. But what is there is enough to make people want to use it, and the foundation has been laid for adding new features that will make it even better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, Periscope is a great app, but what is making it a huge success is how they have handled the development phase. If you like Meerkat or other competitor apps, that&amp;#8217;s great, but the reason why I didn&amp;#8217;t like it, was that I found it overly complex and it just didn&amp;#8217;t feel as smooth and simple to use. It lacks focus. On the flip side, Periscope developers seem to have gotten it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is of course just my point of view, and I would love to hear yours! &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MarcoTroisi/status/639770687045894145&#34;&gt;Let me know&lt;/a&gt; what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-resources:506996eb1ee3dc44d275f124525b4fee&#34;&gt;More resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://michaelhyatt.com/what-i-love-about-periscope.html&#34;&gt;What I love about Periscope&lt;/a&gt; (Michael Hyatt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B014IP8RU2/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B014IP8RU2&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=CWTOFMMUFKNYIKLR&#34;&gt;Periscope Your Biz: Live Video Broadcasting for Profits&lt;/a&gt; &lt;img style=&#34;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&#34; src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B014IP8RU2&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;(Book &amp;#8211; Amazon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Leveraging Twitter&amp;#8217;s Periscope: Join The Community, Build Your Business, and Have Fun!][7] &lt;img style=&#34;border: none !important; margin: 0px !important;&#34; src=&#34;http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=marctroi-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B012H76NMC&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;(Book &amp;#8211; Amazon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B012H76NMC/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B012H76NMC&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=Z4TNTOACIIF5P66N&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B012H76NMC/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B012H76NMC&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=marctroi-20&amp;amp;linkId=Z4TNTOACIIF5P66N&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Code Reviews</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/the-ethics-of-code-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/the-ethics-of-code-reviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Code Reviewing is one of the greatest tools we have as software developers, to help us improve the quality of our code. It can be incredibly beneficial, but it can also be a source of pain and overall, a waste of time instead of a time-saver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like with many things in life, knowing &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we do something, can be a good way to do that thing at its best and not to abuse it. Let&amp;#8217;s begin then to unpack what a code review &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is not your nice, daily half an hour of shooting at your team mates and pointing fingers at their mistakes. If you do code reviews because you find pleasure in finding other people&amp;#8217;s code mistakes or lack of use of best practices, then you shouldn&amp;#8217;t be doing code reviews in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is not a place for &lt;em&gt;teaching&lt;/em&gt;. If you have best practices that you think your team mates should know and use, then there should be a time, prior to starting your project if at all possible, where such best practices and guidelines are established, accepted and understood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is not where discussions should occur. Never mind long and opinionated ones! This is where comments should be kept short and to the point. No repartee, no attempts to justify/defend yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What, then, is code reviewing for? I have outlined &lt;strong&gt;4 points&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a way of &lt;strong&gt;sharing responsibilities&lt;/strong&gt;. When we are code reviewing, we are &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;carrying the weight together&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;, so to speak. We are quitting the old &amp;#8220;I don&amp;#8217;t care, it&amp;#8217;s not my code&amp;#8221; mentality that many of us tend to have, in favour of a &amp;#8220;we&amp;#8217;re in this together&amp;#8221; attitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is a great way to &lt;strong&gt;learn from each other&lt;/strong&gt;. This might, at first sight, seem to be in contrast with the second point of the previous list, but stay with me here: I have learnt &lt;em&gt;so much more&lt;/em&gt; in my career through friendly, non-aggressive opinions and suggestions from my colleagues, than I have from those forceful, unfriendly and aggressive comments from those who thought they knew better than anyone else (or than me, at least). As a matter of fact, not only have I not learnt anything substantial from them, but I have actually &lt;em&gt;hated them&lt;/em&gt; (the comments, not the people!). No matter how good you are, people deserve your respect, and even if they have less experience than you, you were once like them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s where some &lt;strong&gt;bugs and blatant errors are found&lt;/strong&gt;. At the end of the day, this is the real point of doing code reviews. When you do one, focus on finding errors and bugs that whoever wrote the code may have missed, and suggest quick way to fix them. Sometimes you&amp;#8217;ll even find the same error occurring more than once. Resist the temptation to write witty comments like &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;I can&amp;#8217;t believe you&amp;#8217;re doing this again&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;stop doing this for heaven&amp;#8217;s sake!!!!!!&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;. Be professional, and if you think there is something that needs to be discussed, do it personally, in a friendly and not humiliating fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be a way of &lt;strong&gt;improving the code quality&lt;/strong&gt;. As outlined before, best practices should have been priorly discussed, but if you find some piece of code that you reasonably think could be made more efficient, suggest it nicely. A more facultative &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Maybe use &lt;code&gt;function2()&lt;/code&gt;, it would run faster&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; is better than a mandatory &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;replace &lt;code&gt;function1()&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;function2()&lt;/code&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/em&gt; kind of thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, what needs to be remembered is that your collaborators/colleagues/team-mates are professionals like you, regardless of the individual amount of experience. But, ultimately and more importantly, they are human beings! And human beings work better, produce more and tend to be happier in an environment where they are understood, appreciated and respected. And code reviewing can be an incredibly powerful helper in this, if used wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question: what are your rules and what has been your experience with code reviewing? Share your thoughts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=http://www.marcotroisi.com/the-ethics-of-code-reviews/&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http://www.marcotroisi.com/the-ethics-of-code-reviews/&amp;amp;source=tweetbutton&amp;amp;text=%3F&amp;amp;url=http://goo.gl/fDGwIC&amp;amp;via=marcotroisi&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Tips for becoming a Productive Programmer</title>
      <link>http://www.marcotroisi.com/productive-programmer-5-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.marcotroisi.com/productive-programmer-5-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have we not all been there? You&amp;#8217;re struggling to concentrate, the task you are working on is either too boring or too tricky, and you just can&amp;#8217;t seem to go ahead. All you want, after all, is to finish this stuff and move on to the next task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our job is very much brain-dependent. We rarely find ourselves just doing mechanical stuff which doesn&amp;#8217;t really require us to put any thought into it. Usually, what we do requires us to do things like pre-analysis, tracing down the cause of an issue, keeping up with several trains of thought at the same time, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is both a blessing and a curse. On one hand, it is amazingly challenging and stimulating to be able to use our brains to solve problems, and develop solutions. On the other hand, our brains can be so easily affected by our psycho-physical status, that we easily find ourselves having seemingly unproductive days. Even though just a few days before, we were feeling like we could have designed Google from scratch in a couple of hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a theme that&amp;#8217;s important to me, as I myself am the type of person that can be easily distracted and pretty much spend an entire day on a single task without ever really focussing on what I am doing. Then, the next day, I will brilliantly solve &lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; different issues and at end of my day I won&amp;#8217;t even feel tired!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we overcome this? How do we make sure our productivity level keeps being consistent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;getty embed image&#34; style=&#34;background-color:#fff;display:inline-block;font-family:&#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;color:#a7a7a7;font-size:11px;width:100%;max-width:415px;float:right;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div style=&#34;overflow:hidden;position:relative;height:0;padding:55.776173% 0 0 0;width:100%;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p style=&#34;margin:0;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;padding:0;margin:0 0 0 10px;text-align:left;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gettyimages.com/detail/157752806&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; style=&#34;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&#34;&gt;View image&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gettyimages.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; style=&#34;color:#a7a7a7;text-decoration:none;font-weight:normal !important;border:none;display:inline-block;&#34;&gt;gettyimages.com&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s wise to recognise that, as humans, we are susceptible to such ups and downs. If all we were doing in life were working, it might have been easier. But that is not the case. We have lives, issues, passions, hobbies, families outside of the workplace. Which is all fine, by the way, it is what makes us so unique and valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, instead of being too hard on ourselves when our brains just can&amp;#8217;t seem to connect to our work, it can be useful to relax and develop a discipline that will help us deliver quality work even on our worst days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some simple steps I follow in order to make sure my brain understands that I am intentional about being a productive programmer today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wake up early&lt;/strong&gt; Ok, this is harsh, I know. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; sleeping. My whole life, since I was a kid, I&amp;#8217;ve always gotten out of bed at the very last minute. This is so counter-productive! The average successful person &lt;a href=&#34;http://uk.businessinsider.com/things-successful-people-do-before-breakfast-2014-11?op=1?r=US&#34;&gt;wakes up very early&lt;/a&gt;, like 4-5 am. I&amp;#8217;ve started waking up about two hours before I need to be at work. That means that, by the time I get to work, &lt;strong&gt;my brain is already active&lt;/strong&gt; and ready to go. Besides, this has finally solved my life-long problem of never having time for anything else aside from work! I now have enough time to consistently read, write on my blog, work on side-projects, study German (!), etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Morning is for the hard stuff&lt;/strong&gt;: as far as I can, I &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt; anything distracting in the morning. I do not read my emails (yes, I am one of those who is obsessed by always having a clean inbox!), and I have stopped reading the news and stuff like that first thing. I have developed a routine of: turning on my laptop, going to Spotify to choose some music (see point 3), opening my Code Editor and my browser and starting to work. Everything else is a distraction, and the morning is too precious to waste it with anything else. I know I don&amp;#8217;t have the same level of concentration in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not all music is the same&lt;/strong&gt;. I love music. As a musician myself, it&amp;#8217;s too easy for me to get involved into what I am listening! It is ok for 10-15 minutes to listen to your favourite songs. But, ideally, and especially in the morning, I go on the &lt;em&gt;Moods&lt;/em&gt; section of Spotify and I select one of the playlists under &lt;em&gt;Focus&lt;/em&gt;. This is a way of reminding my brain that now it&amp;#8217;s time to work. This type of music really helps me to concentrate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on one small task at a time&lt;/strong&gt;. The key here is to put myself under a little bit of healthy pressure. The thing is, when you are working on one big task, and your expected time of delivery is days ahead, it&amp;#8217;s too easy to lose track, and not to make good use of the time you have. It is way better to focus on one little task at a time, with a delivery time expected in hours, not days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Separate things&lt;/strong&gt;. &amp;#8220;There is a time for everything,&amp;#8221; said King Solomon. In other words, multitasking doesn&amp;#8217;t really work, if you are trying to be productive. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.health.com/health/gallery/0,,20707868,00.html&#34;&gt;Science proved it&lt;/a&gt; as well. There is nothing like dedicating your focus and attention on one thing at a time. Quality makes the difference, in this type of thing. Do what you have to do with absolute focus, finish earlier than expected, and then move on. This practically means things like: not having too many tabs open on my browser, not being involved in 10 different chats with my friends, not checking my phone every 5 minutes, etc&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While doing all of the above things is undoubtedly a challenge, and it is not rare for me to break one or more of these rules, I use them as a blueprint and point of reference, and I get back to them every time I feel I&amp;#8217;m getting less productive than I should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you? What are your tips and tricks for working with greater focus and delivering higher quality work?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>